recently I was doing exactly what you're
doing right now watching a bunch of
YouTube videos comparing different video
editing software and I realized a lot of
them have weird biases towards whichever
software the Creator just switched to
usually they're either excited about how
much faster finally like a pro is gonna
be or if these cool new features that
they're gonna get out of Premiere Pro
also more and more I'm seeing people
talk about switching to DaVinci Resolve
we're not gonna address that in this
video because I just feel like it's not
quite there as a mainstream inally
editor yet it's gonna get there if you
don't spend any money it's amazing go
download it now a quick thank you this
video sponsor CleanMyMac X more about
them later so how are you gonna choose
which software to use you could just
look at a list of features you're ever
gonna find that premier has more things
that it can do it's a longer list that's
not telling the whole story at all I
went and talked to some professional
editors doing some of the best work in
the world and they both made different
software choices thomas grove carter
uses Final Cut Pro when he works for
trim editing based in London he works on
major commercials for Nike outtie
Mercedes and music videos for ed Sheeran
Major Lazer
and more Q have definitely seen his work
he is incredible hey Tyler how you doing
can you tell me a bit about why you
choose to use Final Cut but I found the
Final Cut 10 is the fastest way I'm able
to work as an editor is the only enemy
that I feel really lets me get into a
proper creative flow and just keep
working getting the ideas from my head
onto the screen you've also probably
seen some videos by Johnny Harris he is
doing the Border's series on Vox media
where he travels around the world in his
little documentaries about countries
that he's in and how they interact it's
amazing stuff it's mind-blowing it's
absolutely beautiful he's really
advanced title sequences and he relies
on Premiere Pro and After Effects to get
his work done what I love about premiere
is just the flexibility within it and
the customization that
I can edit a vlog probably in half the
time with final cut if it's
chronological and simple but as soon as
it gets super complicated and I need
four or five six tracks of video to play
around with Final Cut just turns into a
nightmare for me the app itself is
really deep and complex I think it's
kind of everything's like turned off by
default all the settings are hidden or
the all the functions and buttons and
things are just sort of hidden away and
you can pop them all out and all that
complexity is there brand new editors
who've never edited with anything before
pick up Final Cut ten really really
quickly it's people who have known
normal NLE timelines you have to kind of
unlearn a bit of muscle memory and the
way things work as things are a little
bit inverted in borders episodes there
are a ton of visual effects you have a
lot of map animations you have a lot of
titling you have a lot going on a lot
more than I do
what is it about premiere in the Adobe
suite - lets you do that definitely
integration with After Effects is a big
one for me could you do in After Effects
Final Cut workflow no I could I totally
could
more and more I find myself rendering
out MOV files for MP fours from After
Effects so that I've got effectively a
video file
I feel like Final Cut optimizes for
being up to lay down footage in the way
you shot it in a way that is so much
faster and so much smarter but that's
not what orders it is borders is not
it's not a blog it's not chronology it
ends up in some janky renditions that
has nothing to do with chronology it has
to do with topics and story beats that
are that just grouped very differently
and after effects or sorry Final Cut Pro
does not seem to facilitate at least to
my knowledge that's sort of a workflow
that's very very nonlinear when I look
around I can see a lot more examples of
feature films that have used premiere to
edit the feature than Final Cut ten avid
was was or is the standard thing that
people cut in Final Cut 7 came in and
sort of worked of that same meta form
that became popular and I think when
Final Cut ten kind of threw everything
out and decided to reimagine the way
things worked premiere is a great
replacement for that Final Cut 7 and
avid workflow it's kind of it works in
the same way yeah but there have been
big productions that have used final
cuts and I think it's just it's a bigger
commitment from the people who from the
editing department I mean right where I
work now there's a guy who a couple of
editors are working on a like a six-part
channel for Netflix drama here which
they're doing their 50 shoot days
they're getting rushes every single day
and I think big Hollywood studios
probably when things work you kind of
stick with what's working there's no
point rocking the boat actually did try
with the intention of switching and
quickly ran into a ceiling of like man I
feel like I'm learning this but I don't
feel like it it has the capacity to do
it what I need us for my specific
workflow how often do you run into
performance or stability or reliability
issues with Premiere I'll just have like
days at a time where Premiere is just
acting up where it's either freezing or
it's crashing render times certainly are
just it takes a long time like I'm
looking at my 16 minute edit right now
with just chuck full of stuff you know
it's eight layers deep and like
everything and I know every time I want
to render or something now it's gonna be
you know 35 minutes 40 minutes with my
Big Mac tout beast of a laptop and
there's nothing I can do about that
what's something that you do feel
missing from the Final Cut pipeline so
the easy a collaboration with other
editors whether necessarily needs to be
tied to shared storage or if it's
cloud-based I don't know exactly what it
is but kind of a nicer I mean it works
well now we have multiple editors
working on projects and we've got
jellyfish and we kind of share projects
and stuff like that was well but it'd be
nice if there was a bit more of a
seamless way of doing it
thanks so much for your insights Johnny
and good luck with the next episode of
borders so after I did these interviews
I thought I had the whole story figure
it out it's kind of been like this for
years Final Cut is faster and can get
the job done easier it's a little more
elegant but Premiere is more versatile
and just has more stuff that it can do
in total in fact I already tried to
record this video two times basically
saying that test test and then something
weird happened before I was able to
release the video I got this text
message from Johnny just out of nowhere
Hey
I'm in a coffee shop finishing up
borders we'll get into that in a second
but first I want to thank a sponsor of
this video Mac paws latest Mac cleaning
software CleanMyMac X it helps you clean
out all the clutter on your machine and
get it back to running the way that it
did on the day that you bought it and I
guarantee if you're a video editor you
have some clutter sitting around and it
can definitely help with that I've been
using it for years and years and it's
always been able to help me clean out
some of my hard drive find some extra
space when I don't have any left and I
know there is some sketchy Mac cleaning
software out there but Mac paw is an
important part of the developer
community and the software has been
notarized by Apple as being malware free
and it was even voted app of the month
on producthunt I put it on all of my
machines because with the click of a
single button it can do work that takes
you hours to do on your own in the
finder so to find out more click the
link in the description below and thanks
again to CleanMyMac x for supporting
this video hey Tyler I'm in a coffee
shop finishing up orders and I just
outputted the final which I mean look at
this thing it's ginormous
these episodes usually take like 30 to
40 minutes to output and they just
output it into the 10 minutes and this
is like an 18 minute episode so it's
like longer than it's ever been I don't
know what so out of nowhere premieres
performance got way better and then I
saw this other video by Matthew Morris
where she was comparing some really
powerful modern pcs to the MacBook Pro
in getting really surprising results so
I called up Matthew I want to know what
happened I was really surprised so when
I ran these tests I did two specific
tests I render a video and then play
back because how is the timeline gonna
feel when we're editing a video is it
going to be slow are we gonna have a
frustrating experience and to my
surprise the MacBook Pro beat out all
the laptops except for my crazy specked
out desktop PC and it did it by a
considerable amount of time and then
when I did the playback test you know
premiere still drops a lot of frames but
the MacBook Pro happened to drop the
least amount of frames so now it's
interesting I mean it makes it a little
bit harder to choose if premiere isn't
so much slower it takes one of the
advantages away from Final Cut and while
all of this was happening then I saw on
Twitter that Jonathan Morrison is also
working on a video comparing Final Cut
and Premiere so I had to give him a call
to see what he was finding did you find
anything really interesting in your test
like is there anything that you didn't
expect to see I think probably what I
was most surprised with is how maybe how
hard Adobe's working on the Mac side of
things where I feel like there's this
narrative that you know if you want to
use premiere you have to get a PC
because it's optimized to work better
and we built this custom rigged PC build
that it's an awesome machine it's super
powerful but you know if don't like the
20 atti in there that's a really
expensive card and it's powerful for
sure but the performance for what you
would think you would get on the PC side
of things it's not as drastic as you
might think
after doing all this did you find any
simple way to break down a
recommendation for somebody if they have
no predisposition to premiere or final
cut what's something that could help
them choose for me if you're on a Mac
you should use Final Cut just point
blank I don't think there's a better
option in terms of just get out of the
way speed
it's really smart you know with premiere
that was another thing that I noticed
where even you know shooting sixteen by
nine using two to one frames and then
dropping that and a project is one thing
but when I was actually shooting two to
one video in Premiere it won't auto
scale it to the project so it'll just
drop it in and won't know the difference
right and Final Cut you drop it in it
scales it appropriately and those little
things where you're not thinking about
it yeah I think in the in the end it's
not really that interesting whether
people want to get really excited and
angry about different brands but like in
the end you know right she was something
that you end up feeling good about and
when you're using it you feel like
you're able to focus on the job and not
so much on the conversation about
members PC cuz it's not it's not
actually that interesting conversation
already I feel like I could make an
equally awesome video in Premiere it's
not that it's a bad program I just
obviously I'm comfortable in Final Cut
and you know they make great things in
Premiere just it depends on how you use
it the machine you're using it and I
don't think you know it's as unoptimized
or as bad as some people including maybe
my older self would have would have
given it a hard time for I wanted this
to be a pretty straightforward video if
you want these features choose final cut
on these features choose premier but you
know what it's actually kind of hard to
choose these days but I hope this has
helped inform you a bit about why you
might prefer one or the other in the end
they can both do absolutely anything you
want them to you won't be limited by
using either piece of software but the
conversation doesn't have to stop there
all these people have been guests on my
podcast as well and we've gone way more
in depth on topics like this another
creative up schools photography
filmmaking development design whatever
it is you do we've probably talked about
it on the show
Stallman podcast calm I'll see you guys
over there I'll hear you guys or someone
see you or hear you gotta find a better
sign off